Okay. Ready? All right. בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody.
We are on דף קלז, daf kuf lamed zayin, 137.
Pick up with,
no are we on 137? Did I get that right? Okay.
We just had dealt with the debate of רבי Rebbe and רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel about whether when you say
you should get this and אחריך achareicha somebody else, where רבי Rebbe
where they both sort of agree that certainly לכתחילה lichatchila you can't
try to sell. I erased it, but anyway, all right, here's this
person and he says I'm giving it to
you, we decided we were going to become more gender balanced here,
so he's giving it to שרה Sarah and שרה Sarah is giving
it to רחל. Rachel.
And it says אחריך achareicha to you. Okay, and the question is
when he says אחריך achareicha to you, right, does רחל Rachel have
the land and שרה Sarah just have the פירות peirot or because
he says אחריך achareicha means everything is being given to שרה Sarah
and she has the land as well. So everybody agrees that שרה
Sarah only is supposed to sell the פירות, peirot, but if she
actually tried to sell the underlying קרקע karka because he has completely
divested himself of everything, maybe that creates this power vacuum or this
ownership vacuum since רחל Rachel hasn't gotten the קרקע karka yet that
lets her step in. So רבי Rebbe says no, she can't sell
the קרקע, karka, רבי Rebbe basically says, so she's trying to sell
the קרקע karka here, okay, and רבי Rebbe says no, she can't
do it, רבי Rebbe says no because קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף,
kinyan peirot lav k'kinyan haguf,
so she doesn't really own it. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says she can, yes, she is able to, I'll make
this a question mark, okay, because either it's קנין פירות כקנין
הגוף kinyan peirot k'kinyan haguf
or
because אחריך שאני achareicha shani meaning אחריך achareicha equals you actually have
the land with the פירות. peirot. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says she is able to sell. So then the גמרא
Gemara says well what would be if שרה Sarah rather than trying
to and then if she sold she broke the chain and רחל
Rachel loses out. And we said somebody who tries to advise שרה
Sarah like that is a רשע ערום rasha arum because you're hurting
somebody and it's not even in your own best interest. שרה Sarah
לכתחילה lichatchila shouldn't do it, but if she does it we might
not say it was the most wonderful thing to do, but we're
not going to call her a רשע. rasha. Now, what if however
rather than trying to give it to this
person as a gift, she tries to give it to him as
a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat shchiv mera. So then the question is
what order, when does אחריך achareicha kick in and when does the
מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera kick in? So the גמרא Gemara
imagines here, right, like sort of three stages. Okay, here she is
on her deathbed.
So here she's dying, okay, but she's alive, okay, then is moment
of death, okay, okay, I guess here we'll draw what do you
say, I'm going to draw little X's in her
eyes, okay anyway, moment of
death, okay, and then there is after death, she's already died. Tombstone?
Okay, yeah, I don't know, okay fine. All right, anyway, fine. So,
okay anyway, fine. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, that it
assumes that אחריך achareicha kicks in, okay, when does אחריך achareicha kick
in? After she's no longer alive. So kicks in at the moment
of death. At the moment of death, because it's after she's no
longer alive, at the moment of death, it goes to, it would
go to רחל. Rachel. A מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera the
גמרא Gemara is assuming is going to be after death, because remember
the classic way the גמרא Gemara described a מתנה matna which is
like a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera is מהיום ולאחר מיתה,
mehayom ule'achar mita, after death. So it says that actually if she
tried to do that, רחל Rachel would get it before this gift
would kick in because, what did she do? She tried to give
מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera to this person, okay, she can't
break, according to that she did not succeed in breaking the chain,
because אחריך achareicha to רחל Rachel kicks in at the moment of
death and מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera kicks in after death.
Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara said, and that's what leads
us to this really interesting question about A, conceptualizing it as these
separate moments. Okay, it's not alive and dead, there's almost like a
בין השמשות, bein hashmashot, so there's a moment of
transition where you're no longer alive but it's not after you've died,
it's the moment of death, right, so anyway conceptualizing it that way.
And then also, but then also sort of discussing when at which
stage does מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera kick in. So let's
take a look at this, let's pick up from that point again.
The גמרא Gemara says
like
this, ומודה, umodeh, okay,
אמר רבי.
amar Rebbe.
Right, correct. Okay, so we do rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, but ומודה, u'modeh, but רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel agrees
שאם נתן במתנת שכיב מרע לא עשה כלום, she'im natan b'matnas shechiv
mera lo asah klum, that if he tried to give it rather
than giving it as a gift to this other person, but to
give it as a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shechiv mera, he did
not break the chain. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, מתנת שכיב מרע לא קני אלא לאחר מיתה, matnas
shechiv mera lo kani ela l'achar misa, 'cause that takes place after
death, וכבר קדמו אחריך. v'kvar kadmo acharecha. And the אחריך acharecha chain
took place at the moment of death. Okay, so that beat her
out. So וכבר קדמו אחריך. v'kvar kadmo acharecha. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ומי אמר אביי הכי? u'mi amar Abaye hachi? Did אביי Abaye
really say that? והא איתמר, V'ha itmar, it was said, מתנת שכיב
מרע, matnas shechiv mera, מאימתי קני? me'imatai kani? When does it work?
אביי אמר עם גמר מיתה, Abaye amar im g'mar misa, at the
moment of death, ורבא אמר לאחר גמר מיתה, v'Rava amar l'achar g'mar
misa, after death.
Okay, now by the way, partly it could be like it's not
clear why you should say one or the other, but it could
be what's pushing אביי Abaye to say at the moment of death
or rather than after death is because remember at the end of
the day this is not the תורה's Torah inheritance. We might all
agree that the ירושה yerusha in the תורה Torah is after death.
After somebody dies, right, that's how we would say it, after the
person has died, then it passes on to so-and-so. But this is
a מתנה, matana, this is a gift that a person is given.
And the whole problem is, right, the רבנן Rabbanan are trying to
give the person the power to give a gift but make it
like a bequest, right, make it like an inheritance. But a gift
that somebody can give they can only give while they're alive. You
can't give a gift to take place after your death, it's no
longer yours then and you no longer have the power to give
it. So it could be that because on the one hand they're
trying to make it approximate or be modeled after a ירושה, yerusha,
but on the other hand it's with the power of a live
person's ability to give a gift, right, that's how a מתנת שכיב
מרע matnas shechiv mera works, could be the compromise is to say
we're gonna make it take place during this grey period. It's not
after you die—how could you give a gift that takes effect after
you died? Okay, but but we could try to say let's get
it as close to possible as that moment,
as when you're dead also you're dead.
I mean—no, it's at the moment of death. Notice how they say
עם גמר מיתה, im g'mar misa, at that moment when the death
is completing. So it's a very vague time. What do you mean,
is he dead yet or is he is he alive yet? Well,
neither, he's it's the moment of death. So because it's that בין
השמשות bein hashmashos time, it could be that allow—that's like the closest
we can get. I think that would be what would be pushing
us to say עם גמר מיתה im g'mar misa rather than לאחר
גמר מיתה l'achar g'mar misa because at the end of the day
this is a power of the person's ability as an agent to
give a gift, it's not something that happens naturally after he dies.
Yes, Rabbi Droy.
I guess I was just thinking exactly what you were saying, but
conceptually I get it, but practically it's so ambiguous, like are we
talking about a matter of
split seconds or like how do you really determine the moment, the
exact moment?
Right, nobody can actually pinpoint it, and first of all we discussed
it the other day, you know, all these discussions about brain death
or whatever and everybody always says it's like it's not like that
there's you go from alive, dead, like there's like, you know, if
like you turn off a light, like you know, it either was
giving light or it wasn't, there's no moment in between. But death
is like a process, you know, but even if there was like,
you know, I think חז"ל Chazal even if it weren't like a
precise second in time that could be sliced out, I think they're
just conceptualizing it as two stages: there's the moment of death and
then there's after death. Okay, could be that they don't think that
there's a split second that is the moment, right, they could think
it goes from alive to dead, but conceptually you know we're sort
of saying was it at that moment or was it after he
was that status was already sort of taken place? Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: okay, ומי אמר אביי הכי? u'mi
amar Abaye hachi? Now did אביי Abaye really say that? ואיתמר מתנת
שכיב מרע מאימתי קני? v'itmar matnas shechiv mera me'imatai kani? אביי אמר
עם גמר מיתה. Abaye amar im g'mar misa. He says at the
moment of death, not after death. ורבא אמר לאחר גמר מיתה, v'Rava
amar l'achar g'mar misa, after the death has completed. So the גמרא
Gemara says הדר ביה אביי מההיא. hadar beih Abaye me'hahi. אביי Abaye
reversed himself. אביי Abaye in the end decided that it was after
death and it was not in the moment of death. Okay, so
everybody now, אביי Abaye and ורבא Rava are agreeing that מתנת שכיב
מרע matnas shechiv mera is fully like a fully like a you
know a normal inheritance, a normal transfer of property after death, and
it's after death, it's not at the moment. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says ממאי דמההיא הדר ביה? mimai de'me'hahi hadar beih? Who told
you that אביי Abaye reversed himself from this debate with ורבא Rava
and he wound up agreeing with ורבא? Rava? דילמא מהא הדר ביה?
Dilma me'ha hadar beih? Maybe he reversed himself by saying וכבר קדמו
אחריך. v'kvar kadmo acharecha. Maybe he... He actually would say no, this
is at the moment of death, and this is at the moment
of death, and they split it? How do you know he's given
up his position of the moment of death and saying that it's
now taking place after death? So the גמרא Gemara says, לא סלקא
דעתך, lo salka datach, it doesn't make sense that he any people
would say a מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera is the moment
of death, it makes sense to assume that everybody wants to say
it's after death. It's after the person's already dead. Why? דתנן, detnan,
we taught. Now this is not exactly the same, because this is
a גט get and this is a מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat shchiv
mera. זה גיטך אם מתי. ze giteich im mati. A person's on
his deathbed and he says to his wife, this is your get
if I die. Now if he says מהיום אם מתי, mehayom im
mati, great, it's as of today if I die from this death,
and again it's to save her from יבום yibum or whatever. If
it is a second before I die, also great. But if it's
if I die, without saying as of today, so there's always a
question of do you read the word if to mean if and
when, or do you mean as of now if I die? If
it means if and when I die, then the question is what
exactly moment do you mean? A second before you die, the moment
of death, after you're already dead? If it certainly if it means
after you're already dead, it will be too late for it to
take effect. So he says, this is your get if I die.
זה גיטך מחולי זה, ze giteich mecholi ze, this is your get
again of literally of this sickness, meaning if I don't get better
from this illness, but again it might but because he doesn't but
the question is what's the when of the get, and it might
mean if and when I die. So when I die from this
illness, if and when I die from this illness. זה גיטך לאחר
מיתה, ze giteich le'achar mita, the last one is explicit, after I'm
already dead. ולא אמר כלום, velo amar klum, he didn't say anything.
Now what does that prove? So it this there's two very huge
assumptions that the גמרא Gemara is making here. Assumption number one is
is that if somebody tries to give a get עם גמר מיתה,
im gmar mita, not לאחר גמר מיתה, le'achar gmar mita, עם גמר
מיתה, im gmar mita, it might actually be effective. It might be
good. Now that's like wild, right? Because then it sounds like that
עם גמר im gmar I mean I would have said I don't
know, ספק מגורשת, safek megureshet, like if the way I'm trying to
explain it that it's just like gray transition period, why would I
assume a get would be good? Like you know, I would assume
the only way I'm sure get is good is if if I
consider him to be alive. The moment of death, right?
I would assume that's like it's you know it's not it's not
good. So even in fact, so the גמרא Gemara is assuming that
were it to mean עם גמר מיתה im gmar mita the get
would be good. So either one of two things, either the גמרא
Gemara is not assuming that, but it would be assuming if it
said עם גמר מיתה im gmar mita at least it would be
ספק מגורשת, safek megureshet, not וודאי אינה מגורשת. vadai einah megureshet. Maybe
it would be assuming it would be doubtful. Or maybe we've misexplained
it. Maybe עם גמר מיתה im gmar mita does not mean the
moment of death, maybe עם גמר מיתה im gmar mita means a
second before I die, right? That would make a lot more sense,
then a get could be good. עם גמר מיתה im gmar mita
is a is an ambiguous phrase, right? I've translated עם גמר מיתה
im gmar mita mean at the moment of death. But עם גמר
מיתה im gmar mita means with the completing of the death.
But this משנה mishnah doesn't use that phrase.
I understand, but the גמרא Gemara is using the case of a
get to prove that from a get you see that it takes
effect after death and not עם גמר מיתה. im gmar mita. The
basic structure of the גמרא's Gemara evidence is, here's this get that
doesn't work. So it's clear in the get case it takes effect
after death, not with death. And because by by the get case,
logically that should be true by the שכיב מרע shchiv mera case.
So there's two assumptions. The second assumption we'll get to in a
second. Why just because it's true by get is it the same
by שכיב מרע? shchiv mera? Okay, but the first assumption is you
see from the get it's לאחר מיתה le'achar mita and it's not
עם גמר מיתה, im gmar mita, okay?
Because it says לאחר מיתה לא אמר כלום. le'achar mita lo amar
klum.
Right. So you see and but you see all those cases are
treated as לאחר מיתה le'achar mita and therefore not effective. Right. So
therefore even in a case where a person says זה גיטך אם
מתי, ze giteich im mati, the גמרא Gemara imagines, okay let me
step back one step further, maybe I I rushed it too quickly.
The structure of the גמרא's Gemara argument is the following: is that
a person is saying זה גיטך אם מתי. ze giteich im mati.
So it assumes that is just like a שכיב מרע shchiv mera
that says I am giving this to you as a gift if
I die from this illness. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
so whenever if the same time the same time if a person
says זה גיטך אם מתי ze giteich im mati that get would
take effect would be the same time period that if a person
on his deathbed is saying I am I am you know giving
this to you as a deathbed bequest that they would both take
place at the same time. Now why it assumes that I have
no idea. You know, in one case you didn't say אם מתי
im mati the other case you did, one case is a get,
the other case is a special mechanism of a מתנת שכיב מרע,
matnat shchiv mera, but somehow the גמרא Gemara imagines that whatever's true
about this get scenario, when it takes effect at the guy's deathbed,
is true about the מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shchiv mera when it
takes effect. So the גמרא Gemara gives three scenarios of the guy's
deathbed, but it assumes they're all the same. It assumes a get
a get given on a guy's deathbed with the intent that it
should take effect you know at death, takes effect after death, אחר
גמר מיתה. achar gmar mita. And therefore if that's true of a
גט get given on a guy's deathbed, then it should also be
the case by a gift of a שכיב מרע. sh'chiv mera. So
you see that a gift of a שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera is
אחר גמר מיתה. achar g'mar misa. That's the structure of the גמרא's
Gemara argument. So problem number one is, which I don't have an
answer to, is why the heck does the גמרא Gemara assume that
the same mechanism that works from a גט get works for מתנת
שכיב מרע? matnas sh'chiv mera? A מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera
is a special rabbinic institution and they could have gone ahead and
said that it works in cases that a גט get doesn't work,
right? And they could have gone ahead and, you know, and maybe
I don't even use the same language. By the גט get I'm
saying אי מתי, imesi, by מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera maybe
I'm saying nothing, I'm just saying I'm giving you this and you
this and that person that. So why the גמרא Gemara assumes that
the timing of the deathbed גט get is an evidence to the
timing of the deathbed מתנת שכיב מרע matnas sh'chiv mera is not
at all clear in my mind. That's point number one. Okay, but
that's clearly the assumption the גמרא Gemara is making. But point number
two, which I really want to point out, is that why does,
how does the גמרא Gemara know that the deathbed גט get is
אחר גמר מיתה achar g'mar misa and not עם גמר מיתה, im
g'mar misa, right? Maybe the deathbed גט get is עם גמר מיתה
im g'mar misa and it's still no good. So right? But how
does the גמרא Gemara know that it doesn't mean that? So one
of two possibilities. One is if it were עם גמר מיתה im
g'mar misa then maybe it should be a ספק גט, safek get,
that moment of death is that gray period, so why does it
say it's ודאי vadai not good, it should say it's a ספק
גט? safek get? And possibility number two, and this is the real
point I want to bring out because I want to challenge our
assumption, is maybe עם גמר מיתה im g'mar misa for the גמרא
Gemara does not mean the moment of death, does not mean that
there's this gray period. Maybe עם גמר מיתה im g'mar misa for
the גמרא Gemara means a second before death, okay? And if it
means a second before death, then it would totally work for a
גט, get, okay?
And then you'd have that by שכיב מרע sh'chiv mera too, okay,
meaning both, right? What does that phrase in the גמרא Gemara עם
גמר מיתה im g'mar misa mean? It's not clear. It could mean
the גמרא's Gemara conceptualizing these three periods and this is moment of
death and thinks that or could just mean no, there's only two
periods and עם גמר מיתה im g'mar misa just means right before
you transition from being alive to being dead. Okay, so that's not
clear, but it seems on the גמרא Gemara that if a גט
get was meant to take effect עם גמר מיתה, im g'mar misa,
it would not be ודאי vadai not good. It might be ספק
safek good, ספק safek not good. That's what I'd like to argue,
that it's a gray zone and it would be a ספק. safek.
Or it might be ודאי vadai good, maybe עם גמר מיתה im
g'mar misa means a second before death. Okay, but one way or
another the גמרא Gemara is asserting that since you see the גט
get is ודאי vadai not effective, we see by the גט get
case on the deathbed that it's אחר גמר מיתה. achar g'mar misa.
And since the deathbed case of a גט get is אחר גמר
מיתה, achar g'mar misa, the deathbed case of a מתנת שכיב מרע
matnas sh'chiv mera is אחר גמר מיתה, achar g'mar misa, not עם
גמר מיתה, im g'mar misa, but אחר גמר מיתה. achar g'mar misa.
And therefore the גמרא Gemara concludes that אביי Abaye retracted himself and
both אביי Abaye and רבא Rava would agree that the deathbed שכיב
מרע sh'chiv mera is אחר גמר מיתה, achar g'mar misa, and therefore
in this case רחל Rachel gets it עם גמר מיתה im g'mar
misa and her deathbed bequest here does not interrupt the chain because
this would have only transferred אחר גמר מיתה achar g'mar misa and
רחל Rachel the אחריך acharecha will get it עם גמר מיתה. im
g'mar misa. Yes, Jenna, question.
Why don't we read עם גמר מיתה im g'mar misa as from
now if I die?
Oh, no because it's עם im with an עין. ayin. Yeah, it's
my pronunciation. I didn't say
אם.
im. You know what I mean like when you're really finished or
a second before? What? The other times in the גמרא Gemara when
it's גמר g'mar anything doesn't it mean that, you know, when you're
finished and not a second before?
I understand, I'm just trying to make sense about why the גמרא
Gemara thinks that the גט get case proves that it's אחר מיתה
achar misa and not גמר מיתה. g'mar misa.
Does הוא hu mean he's half dead?
Half dead, right. Yes, okay, yeah. All right, so now we continue.
Okay, so that was a really important question about when does, what
this concept of this period called גמר מיתה g'mar misa as opposed
to אחר מיתה, achar misa, and number two, when does מתנת שכיב
מרע matnas sh'chiv mera take effect? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
goes back though to the רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel. And the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רבי זירא אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Amar
Rabbi Zeira amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha k'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Like we
said before, like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said before, we rule like
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that at least in
a case of אחריך, acharecha, the person actually has it and can
sell it away.
ואפילו היו בהן עבדים והוציאן לחירות. V'afilu hayu bahen avadim v'hotzian lecheirus.
So now let's say שרה Sarah was given not just some fields,
but slaves.
So remember, if she sells them off, right, if it's אחריך acharecha
to רחל Rachel or whatever, then we're going to assume that אחריך
acharecha again means she's got the גוף, guf, that's how we've explained
it. Maybe קנין פירות kinyan peiros would not suffice, but אחריך acharecha
means she's got the גוף, guf, so she can sell it off
if she wants. If they were slaves, she could free the slaves
and that would also break the chain. So the גמרא Gemara says
פשיטא, p'shita, of course, I mean once she owns it, she owns
it. Of course, to מהו דתימא, mah de seima, no. מהו דתימא
אמר ליה למיבדי איסורא לא עבידנא לך קא משמע לן. Mah de
seima amar lei l'mivdi issura lo yavidna lach ka mashma lan. No,
maybe the gifter can say, I... I gave them to you, okay,
it's one thing to say you're not going to let the chain
continue to רחבא, Rachava, which is what I wanted, fine. At the
end of the day, I gave them to you, you can do
what you want, but I certainly did not give it to you
to think you would do an איסור issur with them. Now what
would be the איסור? issur? According to the גמרא, Gemara, there's an
איסור issur to free a slave, so it's one thing to give
it an עבד כנעני, Eved Kena'ani, an איסור, issur, which is obviously
conceptually very, very difficult because we like to read the Torah's whole
narrative about slavery, that the Torah's coming to try to correct the
whole institution, you know, and the whole thing from the very beginning,
אנכי ה' אלוהיך אשר הוצאתיך מארץ מצרים מבית עבדים, Anochi Hashem Elokecha
asher hotzeiticha me-eretz Mitzrayim mi-beis avadim, and like the first מצוה mitzvah
in משפטים Mishpatim is about freeing your Hebrew slaves after seven years
and even the Canaanite slaves, it's about ethical treatment of them and
so on. So the reason, the way the חז"ל Chazal read in
that there's a prohibition to free slaves, which is not explicit in
the פסוקים psukim by any means, anyway is something I think we
can find challenging. But anyway, regardless, that's how the גמרא Gemara understands,
so maybe you could say, look, it's one thing I gave them
to you, your property, I wanted it to go to רחבא, Rachava,
you gave it to somebody else, fine, you're entitled. Okay, but I
didn't want you to do an איסור issur with them. Okay, so
it's so funny, I mean once you gave it, you gave it,
but that's fine. קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. Okay, that you
can even free the slaves. אמר רב יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rav Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan, הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל, halacha ke-Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel, ואפילו עשה תכריכים למת. ve-afilu asa tachrichim le-meis.
Even if, you know, what was given I don't know to Sarah
here was cloth, and she decided to turn the cloth and make
it into תכריכים, tachrichim, shrouds. Now she can do that. So the
גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, obviously, now. By the way, the reason
that would be relevant here is it breaks the chain to רחבא,
Rachava, because once they become shrouds, they become אסור בהנאה, assur be-hana'ah,
so רחבא Rachava can't take them for her own use anymore. So
technically they're not owned by somebody else, but they're out of רחבא's
Rachava control. So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, it's obvious, isn't
that just a straight application of the fact that Sarah here has
control over them and owns them? No, מהו דתימא mahu detaima לשויינהו
איסורי הנאה לא יהבי לך, leshabbinei issurei hana'ah lo yahavi lach, I
didn't give it to you to turn them into things that are
forbidden, I gave it to you so that, you know, you should
benefit from it, somebody else could benefit from it. Okay, קא משמע
לן, ka mashma lan, you can't say that. Which is of course,
all those things is so funny to think that, like, once you
give something, what could be the הוה אמינא hava amina that you're,
you know, well, I didn't want you to use it for this.
But what I would say is, is to remind us, remember the
גמרא Gemara before about the fact that if somebody gifted something and
then they realize that maybe there were different assumptions or whatever, the
guy who gifted something to somebody thinking his son was dead turned
out his son was alive, the גמרא Gemara says אזלינן בתר אומדנא,
azlinan basar umdana, I quoted you the רמב"ם, Rambam, the רמב"ם's Rambam
language is לעולם אומדים le'olam omdim with an א aleph דעת הנותן.
da'at hanosein. We always try to assess the mindset of the one
who's giving the gift. And that's a concept of דברים שבלב אינם
דברים. devarim she-ba-lev einam devarim. When it's a one-sided transaction and it's
a gift, we more care what you were thinking and what you
might have had in mind and intended since the other person wasn't
risking anything, they were just receiving, okay, could more shape the context
in which we assume that this gift was meant. So but the
גמרא Gemara says alright, but at the end of the day we're
not going to
say it's a two-sided
transaction and דברים שבלב אינם דברים, devarim she-ba-lev einam devarim, correct?
And it's a one-sided transaction we say sometimes דברים שבלב devarim she-ba-lev
are דברים, devarim, we're more prepared. In these cases, we don't assume
that that was your דברים שבלב. devarim she-ba-lev. Yeah.
So
could he have made an explicit condition and then...
Oh sure, if you explicitly stipulate it, you can explicitly stipulate anything.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
דרש רבא בר רב חסדא, darash Rava bar Rav Chisda, or in
a minute, אתרוג זה נתון לך במתנה ואחריך לפלוני. esrog zeh nassun
lach be-matanah ve-acharecha li-ploni. Okay, so here is, it's given to Sarah,
so Sarah here, this אתרוג esrog is for you as a gift
and after you it should go to
רחבא. Rachava. Alright, now נטלו ראשון ויצא בו. natalo rishon ve-yatza bo.
So Sarah took it and she's אשכנזי, Ashkenazi, so she makes a
ברכה, bracha, okay, and she uses it to be יוצא. yotzei. Okay,
so was she יוצא? yotzei? So the question is, did she own
it or not own it? When you say אחריך. acharecha. So it
says באנו למחלוקת רבי ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל, banu le-machlokes Rabbi ve-Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel, that's the debate. According to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, he says אחריך שאני, acharecha shani, means you
own it,
so she owns the אתרוג esrog so she could be יוצא. yotzei.
You have to own an אתרוג esrog to be יוצא yotzei on
the first day. And according to רבי, Rabbi, he says no, if
you say אחריך, acharecha, the first one only has קניין פירות. kinyan
peiros. And since you don't actually have title to the אתרוג, esrog,
you only have קניין הפירות kinyan ha-peiros on the אתרוג, esrog, so
it
is a פרי, pri, which is what the גמרא's Gemara going to
get to, so Sarah wasn't יוצא yotzei the מצוה, mitzvah, she didn't
have title according to רבי. Rabbi. So that's what you would naturally
say, but the גמרא Gemara challenges this. מתיב לה רב נחמן בר
יצחק, maskif lah Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, challenges this. עד כאן לא
פליגי רבי ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל התם אלא דmar סבר קניין פירות
כקניין הגוף דמי ומר סבר קניין פירות לאו כקניין הגוף דמי. ad
kan lo pligi Rabbi ve-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel hatam ela de-mar savar
kinyan peiros ke-kinyan haguf dami u-mar savar kinyan peiros lav ke-kinyan haguf
dami. There the debate was that רבי Rabbi held קניין פירות kinyan
peiros is not כקניין הגוף ke-kinyan haguf and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says it is. Either קניין פירות kinyan peiros
is כקניין הגוף ke-kinyan haguf or אחריך שאני, acharecha shani, but one
way or the other the person is considered to have title. And
רבי Rabbi says no, you only have קניין פירות. kinyan peiros. So
that's regarding, can Sarah go ahead and say sell this land off
to somebody else. אלא הכא, ela hacha, but here,
גבי gabei the אתרוג, esrog, אם מפיק לא נפיק ביה למאי יהבית
ליה? im mafik lo nafik bei lemai yahavis leh? If Sarah only
has קנין פירות kinyan peiros on this אתרוג esrog and according to
רבי, Rebbi, here's this אתרוג, esrog, okay, I thought, or whatever, yeah,
there's whatever, okay, anyway, anyway, here's that אתרוג. esrog. Sarah has this
אתרוג. esrog. She doesn't have, according to רבי, Rebbi, she only has
a קנין פירות, kinyan peiros, right? What can you do with a
קנין פירות kinyan peiros on an אתרוג? esrog? You can't eat it,
you can't sell it, you could smell it, so that's an interesting
thing. So like would I, do I have to ask your רשות,
reshus, do I have to ask your רשות reshus to smell your
אתרוג, esrog, right? It's sort of like a זה נהנה וזה לא
חסר zeh neheneh vezeh lo chaser type of thing.
Right. Right?
So anyway, so קנין פירות kinyan peiros on an אתרוג esrog does
nothing for her. So the גמרא Gemara says even according to רבי
Rebbi that normally אחרי acharei is only קנין פירות, kinyan peiros, in
this case we have to assume that the קנין פירות kinyan peiros
that Sarah was given was meant to allow her to be doing
the מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so אם מפיק לא נפיק ביה, im mafik
lo nafik bei, if she's not going to use it to be
יוצא... yotzei... use it to be יוצא? yotzei?
אם מפיק im mafik is יוצא.
yotzei.
יוצא לא יצא ביה, yotzei lo yatza bei, okay, right, so נפיק
nafik is לצאת. latzeis. Yeah. Go out, יוצא. yotzei. Okay, I assume
the reason—it's a good question why does to fulfill your obligation mean
יוצא? yotzei? I assume it means to leave your state of being
obligated, you've known, you've left your state of, like, you know, anyway,
you freed yourself from your obligation, yes, yes.
Just a second, קנין פירות, kinyan peiros, excuse me, she's being given
a field of אתרוגים? esrogim?
No, one אתרוג. esrog.
So then I don't understand what's the difference between קנין פירות kinyan
peiros for something that's just disconnected, what's the difference between that and
like if you're actually being...
Well, if I gave you my car for קנין פירות, kinyan peiros,
the קנין פירות kinyan peiros of my car is the ability to
drive it around. But you don't own it. Right. Okay, but what's
the קנין פירות kinyan peiros of the אתרוג? esrog? I guess you
could use it to scratch yourself or something. But what could you
use that would not actually consume it that would be a use?
The only natural thing would be if it was סוכות Succos to
use it to be יוצא. yotzei. Other things קנין פירות kinyan peiros
has a meaning, right? My table, קנין פירות kinyan peiros is to
use my table, right?
No, they are so annoyingly playful here, right? They use a פרי
pri for קנין פירות.
kinyan peiros. Right. That's what I'm saying.
You can't do anything with it except something
ritual,
conceptualized
קנין פירות kinyan peiros with a גוף guf and the פרי. pri.
It's like פרי מפרי. pri mipri. Okay, בקיצור, bekitzur, אם מפיק לא
נפיק ביה, im mafik lo nafik bei, if you weren't יוצא, yotzei,
למאי יהבית ניהליה, lemai yahavis nihaleh, why did he give it to
her? אלא מפיק דכולי עלמא מודו דנפיק, ela mafik dechulei alma modu
denafik,
even רבי Rebbi would say you're יוצא yotzei ביה. bei. מכרה אכלה
machrah achlah באנו למחלוקת רבי ורבי שמעון בן גמליאל. banu lemachlokes Rebbi
v'Rebbi Shimon ben Gamliel.
The question is if Sarah ate the אתרוג esrog or sold it,
right, that's the classic debate. Does she have a קנין הגוף kinyan
haguf and therefore if she eats it or sells it Rachel loses
out and she was entitled because she had a קנין הגוף, kinyan
haguf, or did she only have a קנין פירות kinyan peiros and
by selling it she violated the conditions and she has to reimburse
Rachel or whatever it is, she never really had a קנין הגוף.
kinyan haguf. Okay, so that's the classic debate. Can Sarah go ahead
and sell it and get rid of it and break the chain?
But everybody agrees even for רבי Rebbi that she can be יוצא.
yotzei. Now the question's why can she be יוצא? yotzei? She doesn't
have a קנין הגוף, kinyan haguf, right? So the רשב"ם Rashbam basically
says the point of the קנין פירות kinyan peiros here is you
should own this אתרוג esrog and have the benefit of the אתרוג
esrog and the benefit is the ability to be יוצא. yotzei. But
it's ironic because the תורה Torah demands, or maybe bizarre, because the
תורה Torah demands it says ולקחתם לכם, u'lakachtem lachem, לכם משלכם, lachem
mishelachem,
you have to own it. So being יוצא yotzei is not a
benefit of it that I can
transfer. Being יוצא yotzei requires ownership. So if I'm not actually giving
you ownership, if I'm saying Michael, here's my אתרוג. esrog. If I
were to lend it to Michael, he wouldn't be יוצא. yotzei. If
I give it to him he is יוצא. yotzei. Michael, I'm not
giving it to you, I'm retaining title. But what I'm doing is
I'm giving you the benefit of using it to be יוצא. yotzei.
It's like that's all very nice. Until I give him title he
doesn't own it, right? So I don't understand here how just because
if it's not a קנין הגוף, kinyan haguf, if it's a קנין
פירות, kinyan peiros, how can you give somebody the פירות peiros benefit
of using it as an owner? Doesn't that require you actually be
an owner? Yes.
Maybe the ambiguity here is the English word owner. The תוספות Tosafot
might be telling me that קנין פירות kinyan peiros like air rights
is a kind of ownership, right?
In other words, but that's קנין פירות כקנין הגוף דמי. kinyan peiros
kekinyan haguf dami. But the גמרא, Gemara, but it doesn't sound like
that. It's not like we're saying like even if... the גמרא Gemara
goes to the intent, אם מפיק לא נפיק למאי יהבית ניהליה. im
mafik lo nafik lemai yahavis nihaleh. The גמרא Gemara isn't saying an
objective reality. קנין פירות kinyan peiros is enough of a קנין הגוף...
kinyan haguf... לכל השיטות lechol hashittos to be יוצא yotzei the מצווה
mitzvah of אתרוג. esrog. It's not saying that. It's saying if you
didn't give it to the person to be יוצא, yotzei, why were
you giving it? Which means this is what you wanted the person
to use it for. It's not saying that as an objective assessment,
קניין הפירות kinyan hapeiros even if it's not כקניין הגוף kekinyan haguf
satisfies the requirements of ownership for אתרוג. esrog. That's not what it's
saying. It's saying clearly you wanted the person to be יוצא yotzei
the מצווה mitzvah of אתרוג, esrog, so it must be that was
the capacity in which you gave it to them. So I think
that sort of begs the question, unless what we're saying is that
this person gave it to such and such צורה tzurah for the
purposes of the מצווה mitzvah of אתרוג, esrog, you have title to
it. For all other purposes, you don't have title to it. That's
different. That's not a קניין הפירות. kinyan hapeiros. That's an actual קניין
הגוף kinyan haguf for this area. That is a possible way of
reading it. Yes.
I thought of reading a third category, which is קניין הגוף kinyan
haguf with conditions. Right?
Or קניין הגוף kinyan haguf for the following purposes. When it comes
to questions of the מצווה mitzvah of אתרוג, esrog, you own the
אתרוג. esrog. I am giving you the title to it. It's not
because of קניין הפירות. kinyan hapeiros. I'm giving you the title to
it for the issue of הלכות אתרוג. hilchos esrog. Okay, right.
The only thing you can't do is sell it or eat it.
Well, the only thing you can't do is everything other than the
מצווה mitzvah of אתרוג. esrog. Right, right. I understand he's contrasting it
to selling and eating, but I think the real point is that's
symbolic of anything
that isn't the מצווה mitzvah of אתרוג, esrog, right? We'd have to
imagine what another scenario would be, but okay, right. Anyway, I think
that's the only way to explain it. But the רשב״ם Rashbam makes
it sound different. He makes it sound like being יוצא yotzei the
מצווה mitzvah is a type of a פרי, pree, and that's what
I'm giving you. And like, I don't understand it. It's a requirement
to own it, so you can't get around that requirement, I would
say, yes.
Yes, I was maybe I misunderstood the question, but how if you
have to own it, then how can you just own part of
it?
Because you're not owning part of it. You're fully owning it for
certain purposes, you know? It's like, look, the גמרא Gemara has, I'll
give you another example the גמרא Gemara has. I've got a slave.
The הלכה halacha is, you know, since we're at slaves, if your
ox gores my slave, you have to give me שלושים שקל. shloshim
shekel. Can I sell my slave to Jenna for the purposes of
if the slave gets gored? For all other purposes, it's my slave.
I completely own it. But in the advent that that slave got
gored, for that purpose Jenna is considered the owner. So you know,
so it's like for nothing else, but you do have to be
the owner. Within those הלכות halachos we're considering you the owner and
nothing else. So the גמרא Gemara actually discusses same type of an
idea, right? You're not really the owner, but within a certain area
of הלכה halacha that demands ownership, we will give you title only
for the purposes of that area of הלכה. halacha. Like insurance.
What do you mean like insurance?
Like I own a business where I would say I will pay
you, wait, whatever, like that
way.
Not like insurance. Right.
Don't you think the רשב״ם Rashbam is saying what we've concluded in
a way?
ולא ניתן לראשון
אלא לקיים בו מצות נטילה ובכך קרינא ביה לכם ושלכם הוא כל
זמן שראוי לצאת בו.
velo nittan
lerishon
ela lekayem bo mitzvat netilah uvechach karina beih lachem veshelachem hu kol
zman sherauy latzet bo.
Maybe, maybe. The emphasis is on this is the singular purpose of
this.
No, if you keep on reading down in the narrow lines, the
line starts with the word, he says like this: לפירי, lepeiri,
about ten lines down the narrow lines. לפירי יהביה ניהליה והיינו פירותיו
לצאת בו לפירי יהביה ניהליה והיינו פירותיו. lepeiri yahavyah nihalei vehaynu peirosov
latzet bo lepeiri yahavyah nihalei vehaynu peirosov.
Being יוצא yotzei is the פרי pree of this אתרוג. esrog. So
that I just find is very difficult. I would not say being
יוצא yotzei is the פרי. pree. I would say it's your אתרוג,
esrog, you totally have title within the area of the מצווה mitzvah
of being יוצא, yotzei, of לולב. lulav. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara goes on, okay? אמר רבה בר הונא האחים שקנו אתרוג
בתפוסת הבית. Amar Rabba bar Huna ha'achim shekanu esrog bitfusas habayis.
You have brothers who inherited an estate and they used the money
of the estate to buy an אתרוג. esrog. Okay, so this אתרוג
esrog is now collectively owned by the brothers. Now what you have
to know is you're not יוצא yotzei with a לולב lulav and
אתרוג esrog of שותפים, shutfim, of partners. But but what's really fascinating
about the idea of תפוסת הבית, tfusas habayis, תפוסת הבית tfusas habayis
is like the moneys of the estate, is that it is the,
I think the one example in הלכה halacha where you have something
similar to a corporation. You have multiple people, but it's owned by
an entity. Right? If something is owned by partners, if this אתרוג
esrog is owned by me and Michael, then he owns fifty percent
of it and I own fifty percent. And it's not לכם, lachem,
it's not fully mine because half of it belongs to Michael. If
Michael and I are brothers and we've inherited an estate, it's not
owned half by Michael and half by me. It's owned by the
estate. And Michael and I, until we divide it, and Michael and
I have a right to sort of divide the estate and take
off its, you know, and sort of split its assets, we're like
shareholders in the estate, but right now it's owned by the estate.
So an idea of an estate is a very interesting, I think,
for you know, because of contemporary
ideas. Right, exactly. And now the question is can we be יוצא
yotzei with it? It's not personally mine, but it's not also half
Michael's and half mine. It's owned by the estate.
שותפות Shutfus is just half mine and half mine.
I understand, I'm contrasting it to that case. Right. Okay. So נטלו
אחד מהן ויצא בה, Natlo echad meihem veyatza bah,
one of them took it and was יוצא, yotzei, means for the
intent of being יוצא. yotzei. Okay, אם יכול לאכלו יצא ואם לאו
לא יצא. im yachol lochlo yatza ve'im lav lo yatza.
If I could eat it without therefore Michael having a fit, okay,
meaning he'd be okay with me eating it, I was יוצא. yotzei.
If not, I wasn't יוצא. yotzei. Now why is that important? So
some would think that one thing to say is eating is just
a way of indicating ownership. I could destroy it. It could have
easily have just said if I could destroy it without Michael or
sell it without Michael having a fit. And that just proves that
basically when I'm taking it, Michael is sort of like, okay, that
could be your אתרוג, esrog, I'll take something else out of the
estate, be my guest, go ahead. And then effectively it's even if
we haven't really divided the estate, there's some implicit sense that's my
I'm taking that out of the estate. All right, then it's not
such an interesting הלכה. halacha. Then it's just telling you that given
the context, since Michael wouldn't object, we read it like I took
that out of the estate to be mine. Then maybe after I
was יוצא, yotzei, maybe I could put it back in the estate
and Michael could do the same because
who knows? But at that stage it was considered to be mine.
I would suggest a slightly different approach, because there's an interesting issue
that comes up in סוכה Sukkah when it discusses
an אתרוג. esrog. One of the הלכות halachos of an אתרוג esrog
is that it has to be ראוי לאכילה. rauy l'achilah. Like if
it's טבל tevel or something of that nature, you're not יוצא. yotzei.
And there's interesting explanations why. Some people say because then it's not
fully לכם. lachem. If you don't have the power to eat it,
then you're not a full or then you don't have real control,
real ownership. רמב"ם Rambam in פירוש משניות Peirush Mishnayos has a very
nice explanation. He says the תורה Torah says ולקחתם לכם פרי עץ
הדר. u'lekachtem lachem pri eitz hadar. And a פרי pri to be
defined as a fruit, it has to mean it has to be
you have to be able to eat it. Now, there's different ways
you're not able to eat it. One is I can't eat it
because it's not כשר, kosher, it's טבל. tevel. Another way I can't
eat it is because I don't have full rights over it. It's
part of an estate. But it is interesting that it says specifically
the idea of eating. So I could suggest that the idea here
is this thing wouldn't work. If Michael and I were partners, let's
imagine it wasn't an estate, Michael and I were partners, okay, we
had an אתרוג esrog x, we sold אתרוגים, esrogim, that was our
partnership. We each gave in 50% of the money and then it
comes time for סוכות Succos and I realize I haven't even taken
one for myself and I take one and I'm יוצא. yotzei. Okay,
if but we haven't split up the split it, it's still owned
50% by Michael. It could be I'm not יוצא yotzei even if
he wouldn't be מקפיד, makpid, even if he would have his own
אתרוג, esrog, because at that stage it's still owned 50% by Michael.
It could be that here it works because it is it's owned
by the estate, by this more abstraction. It's not 50% Michael's, it's
100% the estate, but I'm a sort of member of the estate,
I'm sort of a beneficiary of the estate. So I think it
allows for an interesting way of thinking that it might be a
little different that Michael's ownership might less be seen as compromising mine
because it's more this abstract entity. My ability to eat it, though,
shows that it's not I have enough rights within the estate that
it's enough that it's connected to mine, but Michael's ownership isn't somehow
compromising mine. Anyway, so I think it's a little unclear what exactly
is the principle. Is it uniquely because of the idea that this
is an estate or is it just because once Michael wouldn't object,
it would be the same in a case of a partnership, once
he wouldn't object, it shows that I'm basically taking this out of
the partnership, taking this out of the estate and I am considered
now the sole owner. Okay, so that's the question here.
What if I feel like a couple want to share an אתרוג
esrog or something like that?
Right, like in a family, right. And what, so anything that is
not this idea of a estate, right, your interesting question about the
husband and wife, I mean nowadays we have the joint property idea
and so on, in the time of the גמרא Gemara you didn't.
But right. But, so that's the question, can you abstract this, generalize
this idea of an estate to other types of like partnerships, or
that's what I'm trying to get at, is it uniquely because of
the idea that an estate is its own conceptual entity? And the
other point is whether the eating is indication that you've taken it
out of the estate and you have full ownership, or is the
eating also relevant to the fact that considering it a פרי pri
in an אתרוג, esrog, like this רמב"ם Rambam that I mentioned? Anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: דוקא דאיכא אתרוג לכל חד וחד. davka d'ika esrog l'chol chad
u'chad. That would only be true if Michael had his own אתרוג.
esrog. So then the fact that I'm using it, it's not like
he still is expecting to get it back and it's still partly
keeping his claws in it.
Means the other one had an אתרוג. esrog.
The other one, of all the brothers had their own אתרוגים esrogim
to use, either from the estate or otherwise. So therefore they were
okay for me to take this one.
Meaning like if the two brothers now had three
אתרוגים.
esrogim. Correct. אבל פרישו רימונא Aval perishu rimona
Fine. A quince or a pomegranate loaf. So anyway, רשב"ם Rashbam tells
us don't know what the point of that of this extra line
in the גמרא Gemara is, because the basic point is what it
said before. If you don't mind that I'm taking it and you
wouldn't even mind if I ate it, then that shows that I
am enough of an owner that I'm יוצא. yotzei. So this extra
line is just seen as like, I don't know, some little superfluous.
Now, interesting little historical note, look down in the wide lines of
the רשב"ם Rashbam and go down and look where he says like
this. Where he says, two lines down in the wide lines near
the end. ומנהג שלנו שנהגו לברך כל הקהל באתרוג אחד, U'minhag shelonu
she-nahagu le-vareich kol ha-kahal be-esrog echad,
our practice is that the whole community uses just one אתרוג esrog
because they couldn't get אתרוגים. esrogim. Two lines of the wide lines
of the רשב"ם Rashbam towards the end of the line, now the
beginning of the third line. דעתנו מסכמת לתת כל אחד במתנה את
חלקו לחברו. Da-teinu maskemes le-tein kol echad be-matana es chelko le-chaveiro.
We're implicitly we all own it in partnership, so partnership doesn't work,
but whenever anybody's turn is to take it, everybody else is implicitly
granting that person as a gift their portion in the אתרוג. esrog.
So that that the person every person who takes it at that
moment owns it fully. Okay. כדאמרינן גבי רב יוחנן בן יהושע מסכת
סוכה Ked'amrinan gabei Rav Yochanan ben Yehoshua maseches Sukka ואף על גב
דלא פריש כמאן דפריש דמי. ve-af al gav de-lo parish k'man de-parish
dami. Even if it wasn't explicitly stated, it's implicit. We all buy
this אתרוג esrog in partnership and we're implicitly granting full ownership to
each person who uses it in turn. דלא גריע ממתנה על מנת
להחזיר דהכי מיעד דעת כל הקהל שווים, De-lo gari mi-matana al menas
le-hachzir de-hachi meya'ad das kol ha-kahal shavim, this is how we all
are unanimous, have a consensus, שינתן לכל אחד עד שיברך עליו, she-yinasei
le-chol echad ad she-yivareich alav,
each person should own it fully until he makes the ברכה, bracha,
ואחר כך יחזיר, ve-achar kach yachzir, and then he would give it
back to the joint ownership of the community. Okay and then he
speaks about יום טוב ראשון, Yom Tov rishon, יום טוב שני, Yom
Tov sheini, you don't have to need that etcetera. Back to the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אתרוג זה נתון לך במתנה על
מנת שתחזירהו לי. esrog zeh nosun lach be-matana al menas she-tachzireihu li.
Michael, here, you can use this אתרוג, esrog, classic מתנה על מנת
להחזיר matana al menas le-hachzir is the אתרוג esrog case. Use this
אתרוג esrog only on the condition you give it back to me.
על מנת שתחזירהו לי. Al menas she-tachzireihu li. נטלו ויצא בו, Nitlo
ve-yatza bo,
so Michael took it to be יוצא yotzei והחזירו, ve-hecheziru, and then
he gave it back to me. יצא, Yatza, he was יוצא. yotzei.
לא החזירו, Lo hecheziru, Michael decided to keep it. לא יצא, Lo
yatza, he wasn't יוצא, yotzei, he didn't fulfill the condition, and not
only was he wasn't יוצא, yotzei, now he has a stolen אתרוג
esrog in his hands because I never gave it to him retroactively,
I never I certainly I didn't give him to keep, I never
even gave it to him to use for the מצוה mitzvah if
he wasn't going to give it back to me. So retroactively he's
now... of course the irony is, let's say I now go ahead
and I get the בית דין beis din on him and I
get the police on him and say Michael, you're keeping that אתרוג
esrog away from me, and the בית דין beis din takes it
away from Michael and gives it back to me. Now was Michael
retroactively יוצא? yotzei? Because now he was מחזיר. machzir. Does he have
to be מחזיר machzir to me out of his free will? If
he's trying to keep it, he can no longer say that he
was מחזיר. machzir. What's the point, what is the definition of מחזיר,
machzir, right? It's a good question, right? By the way, this becomes...
if you say it's theft, and then theft something stolen, you can't
use for מצוה? mitzvah?
No, but then retroactively once it was taken away from him and
given back to me, retroactively he was יוצא, yotzei, he did fulfill
the condition, and then at the time whatever...
but I'm saying if he isn't that, couldn't you see that in
the framework that he stole it?
No, at the moment he took it he didn't steal it, it
was only afterwards he decided he wasn't going to give it back
to me.
Right, so if the police then take it and return it to
the owner...
yeah, I don't think that's considered being יוצא. yotzei. Right, I think
the על מנת שתחזירהו לי al menas she-tachzireihu li means willingly. Okay,
but there's a middle point as well. Let's say he wasn't intending
to steal it but he didn't willingly give it back to me.
It was like he took it and he's irresponsible and he left
it in this room and he went and I came back to
the room and said that stupid Michael, it's the last time I'm
giving him my אתרוג, esrog, and I took it back. He never
was trying to keep it from me, he just forgot and he
left it. Was he יוצא? yotzei? Was he מחזיר machzir it to
me? What exactly constitutes being מחזיר machzir is a left-over question. I
don't know, it's a little unclear. By the way, here's an interesting
question that the פוסקים poskim ask. Can I go ahead and take
to my minor child and say here's a לולב lulav and אתרוג,
esrog, בקונה be koneh it, על מנת שתחזירהו לי. al menas she-tachzireihu
li.
And then so the גמרא Gemara says we can't do that be...
well, the גמרא Gemara says I think there's not על מנת להחזיר,
al menas hachzir, it says don't give it to them because they
can't be מקנה makneh it back to you. But I'm not asking
them to be מקנה makneh it back to me. I'm just saying
על מנת שתחזירהו לי. al menas she-tachzireihu li. Does תחזירהו לי tachzireihu
li mean that they have to be מקנה makneh it back to
me? Is it they have to do an act of... of... of
transferring ownership
or just give it back to me? So it's very interesting what
is exactly considered to be the condition.
Did they do this with the אתרוג esrog yesterday?
Yeah, don't do it.
Okay, but it could be if you loan me the 250 dollar
book on כשרות kashrus על מנת al menas that I gotta return
it to you, I leave it on the park bench and go
home and you find it there five minutes later while walking the
dog, that could be considered I returned it to you?
No, no, no. Similar question. One is if you're a borrower, what's
considered to be that you fulfilled your obligation of returning. That's different
than...
Yeah, and
then you come back and get it. Right. And you suffice for
your obligation if he didn't say to you I'm giving it back
to you?
Well, right, that's the related question. Well, either way I do. Either
it constitutes that he's fulfilled the תנאי tnai and now it's mine
again, or he didn't fulfill the תנאי tnai and therefore I never
gave it to him and therefore it was always mine. So me,
I'm good. The question is him. Okay. So, now the גמרא Gemara
says לא יצא, lo yatza, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan מתנה
על מנת להחזיר שמה מתנה. matana al menat lehachzir shma matana. A
gift, because this gets to the question of what's considered ownership. You
could say, remember the גמרא Gemara before? Anything that you can't be
מקדיש makdish isn't a good
מתנה, matana, right? So תוספות Tosfos asked that before, and תוספות Tosfos
says, well you don't really have to be מקדיש makdish it, it
just means that it's not a sham. So that's part of the
חידוש. chiddush. A gift on the condition that it be returned, we
don't say, ah, it's not really a gift, you're just waiting to
get it back, right? The חידוש chiddush of רבא Rava is no,
it is a gift and the person can be considered to be
a full owner and a full title, and then eventually he's got
to return it. But you understand that that's a big חידוש. chiddush.
Naturally you might say any gift that has to be given back
is you never were the full owner. And רבא Rava says no,
you're a full owner with a stipulation that you give it back
eventually.
And you have to return it in the same form that you
got it.
Well that's also true. Correct. ההיא איתתא. hahi itata. Now there was
a woman דהוה לה דקלא בארעא דרביבי בר אביי. dehavah lah dikla
be'ara deRabibi bar Abaye. She had a palm tree in רביבי בר
אביי's Rabibi bar Abaye property. כל אימת דהוה אזלה למיגזרה, kol eimat
dehavah azla lemigzra, every time she wanted to go and harvest the
tree, הוה קפיד עילוה. havah kafid ilavah. רביבי בר אביי Rabibi bar
Abaye would say get out of my land, you're ruining the grass,
now's not a good time, come back later. Okay. אקנייתה ניהליה כל
שני חייו. akniyata nihalei kol shnei chayav.
Now she, for whatever reason, I mean he wasn't seeming like he
was being so nice, she decided to gift him, or maybe it
was sell it, maybe she got some money out of it, not
clear, but one way or another she transferred him ownership of the
tree as long as he was alive. Okay, she said look, he's
never gonna let me go out and harvest the tree anyway. I'm
gonna sell it, maybe again, I hope she got some money out
of it, okay, especially as the way this story is gonna end.
Okay, anyway, so she sold him the tree, she gave him the
tree as long as he was alive and figured after he dies
I'll get it back, get back the ownership and then I'll be
able to harvest the fruit, harvest the fruit without trouble. That was
clear, כל ימי חייו. kol yemei chayav. Okay. אזל איהו אקנייה ניהליה
לבנו קטן. azal ihu akniyah nihalei livno katan. So he went, he
transferred the ownership to his minor son. There's a question of why
minor? Because it's protected in the hand of his minor son, because
his minor son, like I just was saying before, can possess property
but can't transfer it, cannot divest himself of it. So this way
if it's in the hands of his minor son, nobody is gonna
get access to it, because even if the son sold it, it
wouldn't be a valid sale. Okay, so basically the question is, is
this a case of breaking the chain? This woman, here now we
get to switch it, who's the, okay? This is the woman, this
is רביבי בר אביי. Rabibi bar Abaye. Wait,
is that רביבי, Rabibi, right? Okay, and this is his
son, okay, בן רביבי, ben Rabibi, whatever, okay. Anyway, big small small
kid. Anyway, so the point is, okay wait wait no no. That's
what he did, excuse me, excuse me, this, this is his son.
Excuse me, this is his son. Who is the אחריך acharecha in
this picture? This רביבי Rabibi transferred it to his son. Who is
the אחריך? acharecha? She. She is.
She's her own אחריך. acharecha. Okay, so according to רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel did he break the chain and now
even after he dies she won't get it back? That's the question.
But there's an interesting thing that he's a קטן katan because he's
not really getting it.
Well he is, a קטן katan especially על ידי אחר, al yedei
acher, a קטן katan can be קונה. koneh. He can't be מקנה
makneh but he can קונה. koneh. That's the משנה. mishna. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. So אזל איהו אקנייה ניהליה לבנו. azal
ihu akniyah nihalei livno. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav
Huna brei deRav Yehoshua, משום דאתו ממולאי, mishum de'atu miMulai, because you
רביבי בר אביי Rabibi bar Abaye come from this place called ממולא,
Mamula, that was the name of the place, okay, אמריתו מילי מולייתא.
amritu milei mulyata. You say ממולא Mamula words. So the רשב"ם Rashbam
says either that means like, he has two explanations what that means,
either it means
like a, what does he say, two explanations what it means, he
says either, either
like a cut down words, comes from a word of like to
harvest or to cut down, or it means like a bumpy words,
like a, you know, perverted words. Anyway, it wasn't a compliment, whatever
it was. Because you come from this place of ממולא, Mamula, you
say, because whatever, you come from wherever, you know, your words, you
know, your words are as stinky as the place you come from.
Okay.
Because he was a descendant of עלי. Eli. Why? Well, that's the
הכהן. haKohen. Right, so they lived in this place, correct.
Now
why is that not a good position? אפילו רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
לא קאמר אלא לאחר. afilu Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel lo ka'amar ela
le'acher. Even if according to,
it's not because she's her own אחריך, acharecha, that's fine, but when
do you break the chain when you sell it to somebody who's
not considered a continuation of you? Selling it to your son is
still keeping it within, does not say, oh there's no more אחריך,
acharecha, the chain was broke because you know it's now somebody else.
No, your child is still considered under your pro- domain or in
your ownership and therefore after you die it will go back to
her. You didn't break the chain.
Even if it's been
sold to a son who's independent? Apparently. You're right, you could make
that חילוק, chiluk, but apparently. Okay, so that's what he says. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, let's just okay it's eighth day but let's just
read one more line because it's
and he wouldn't work and and he gets it back.
Let's just read one more line because this is gets back to
the original case. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, look at that, we went
from being a דף daf ahead to being behind. אמר רבא אמר
רב נחמן, Amar Rava amar Rav Nachman, שור זה נתון לך במתנה
על מנת שתחזירהו לי. shor zeh natun lach bematanah al menat shetachzirehu
li. Michael, here's an ox, it's a gift, make sure you get
it back on the condition you get it back to me. That's
מתנה על מנת להחזיר. matanah al menat lehachzir. הקדישו והחזירו הרי זה
מוקדש ומוחזר. Hiktisho vehachziro harei zeh mukdash umuchzar.
Michael is מקדיש maktish it and then he gives it back to
me. Good job, his ox! So he satisfied the condition and now
I have a הקדש hekdesh ox because he was able to be
מקדיש maktish it because because it was his. So גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, amar lei Rava leRav Nachman, מאי אהדרי?
mai ahadrei? What what did he give him back? He gave him
back, this is the idea of in the same condition, he gave
him back an ox he can't use. That's not considered satisfying the
condition. אמר ליה, Amar lei, ומאי חסרי? umai chasrei? What what did
he lose out? Now some take out those words, what do you
mean ומאי חסרי? umai chasrei? Of course חסרי. chasrei.
I mean he looks as healthy and
hale, maybe, he still eats food on the שוק. shuk. Alright, maybe.
אלא אמר רב אשי, Ella amar Rav Ashi, חזינן. chazinan. אי אמר
ליה על מנת שתחזירהו, Ei amar lei al menat shetachzirehu,
on the condition you give it back, אהדרי, ahadrei,
he gave it back. אי אמר ליה על מנת שתחזירהו לי, Ei
amar lei al menat shetachzirehu li,
you give it back to me, מידי דחזי לי קאמר ליה, midi
dechazi li ka'amar lei, it has to be fit for me. So
if I said על מנת שתחזירהו, al menat shetachzirehu, you give it
back and now I have a הקדש hekdesh ox, you satisfied the
condition. If I said על מנת שתחזירהו לי, al menat shetachzirehu li,
here's the irony, I want you to just end by pointing out
the circular nature. He's מקדיש maktish it, he hasn't satisfied his condition,
so he gives it back to me. So because he didn't satisfy
his condition, I never gave it to him. Because I never gave
it to him, he wasn't מקדיש. maktish. Since he wasn't מקדיש, maktish,
okay, so therefore we don't say it ends there. It's mine, I
never gave it to him, he wasn't מקדיש. maktish. So now I
can use it. But why don't we just keep on going with
that cycle? Oh, so he wasn't מקדיש, maktish, so then he didn't
satisfy his condition, so then I didn't, anyway, we don't say that.
Alright, so we will end with this, that if I say לי,
li, then you didn't satisfy your condition and it's not קדוש, kadosh,
and if I did say, didn't say לי, li, you did satisfy
your condition.